<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Posts on Marichikā</title>
        <link>https://arunkpatra.io/posts/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Posts on Marichikā</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <language>en-us</language>
        <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://arunkpatra.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
        <item>
            <title>Dharmarāja</title>
            <link>https://arunkpatra.io/posts/2020/07/dharmaraja/</link>
            <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://arunkpatra.io/posts/2020/07/dharmaraja/</guid>
            <description>Prologue The Indian way of life is woven with yarns of a multitude of faiths, beliefs and convictions. If the warp of our culture’s fabric is rationale, the weft has to be belief. That fabric is dyed with hues of tradition and rituals, and block printed with rich patterns from Hindu mythology. An extraordinarily rich and complex cultural canvas is the result.
Hindu mythology just like Egyptian, Greek or Norse mythology, plays a very important role in carrying forward human culture.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="prologue">Prologue</h2>
<p><em>The Indian way of life is woven with yarns of a multitude of faiths, beliefs and convictions. If the warp of our culture’s fabric is rationale, the weft has to be belief. That fabric is dyed with hues of tradition and rituals, and block printed with rich patterns from Hindu mythology. An extraordinarily rich and complex cultural canvas is the result.</em></p>
<p><em>Hindu mythology just like Egyptian, Greek or Norse mythology, plays a very important role in carrying forward human culture. It’s not only a way of preserving what has come to pass, but also a great source of inspiration and knowledge for the present and future. While the root word of mythology is myth, mythology itself is probably not just myth. Even if it were, isn’t it just beautiful?</em></p>
<p><em>In Hindu mythology, Dharmarāja, Yamarāja or Yamā, is the God of Justice. He is also the God of death. He is the ultimate judge of the ultimate court and has the responsibility of handing down judgement based on our deeds. He is the keeper of the celestial laws. His purview of justice encompasses everything, the known and the unknown.</em></p>
<p><em>So, enjoy this little story from the past, way, way before you and I were here…</em></p>
<h2 id="the-weeping-child">The weeping child</h2>
<p>The infant wailed on a stormy August evening. Her elder sister tired of hunger, just slept off when she could bear it no more. Beside her, lied their mother, holding on to the last remaining breaths of life she had, waiting for the yamādootā. The father had succumbed to illness last summer, leaving the family in abject poverty and despair.</p>
<h2 id="go-at-once-said-yamā">Go at once, said Yamā</h2>
<p>In Yamalokā, Yamā’s abode, the lord ordered the yamadootā. “Go at once, and return promptly with her soul. It’s just about time”. The yamadootā appeared magically at the woman’s doorstep in a while. The kid wailed. But something happened that had never happened to the yamadootā. He was overwhelmed with the misfortune and pain of the two young girls he saw. “I can’t take the mother away. These fatherless children won’t possibly survive without their mother. No I can’t take this woman’s soul”. And the yamadootā returned to Yamalokā empty handed.</p>
<p>“Where is her soul?”, thundered Yamā. “Oh Lord, I could not bring her soul.” Said the yamadootā shuddering with fear. Yamā was not convinced with his account and said, “Yamadootā, your job was to carry out orders. A living beings life is governed by the laws of nature and God’s will. Death is the ultimate truth, and I am the keeper of that ultimate truth. You have not only failed in your duty, but also have disobeyed God’s will. You have interfered with the laws of nature. You will have to atone for your sins. You are hereby relieved of all your heavenly duties and powers. You are expelled from yamalokā and will go to mrityulokā at this very moment. There, you will live the life of a mortal. Your penance will be over when you truly understand why I am expelling you from yamalokā at the first place. Until then you must suffer all the pangs of mortality in mrityulokā.</p>
<h2 id="the-cobblers-son">The cobbler’s son</h2>
<p>The yamadootā, found himself in the much familiar environs of earth where he had travelled numerous times to ferry souls. In that wintery night, he now shivered beneath a tamarind tree near a cobbler’s hut. The cobbler had been to the market to buy a woolen blanket for his son, for the weather was unbearably chilly. As he passed his hut, blanket in hand, the cobbler saw a man shivering in that chilly night. Taking pity on this unfortunate, homeless man, he gave away the blanket. Hearing this, the cobbler’s wife shouted with rage. “You have no brains, and have no love for my son. How is he going to sleep in this chilly night?” The cobbler could not argue much, and went to sleep.</p>
<h2 id="the-kings-shoes">The king’s shoes</h2>
<p>The yamadootā, now the hungry, homeless man in mrityulokā, took refuge in the cobbler’s house the next day. He slept beside the dog, and he and the dog ate happily whatever leftovers were thrown out everyday. And the homeless man observed from a distance, as the cobbler went about his business making shoes. Everyday, he learnt a knew thing about shoe making. And once when the cobbler was down with fever, much to his amazement, the homeless man had made a pair of unbelievably beautiful shoes. The homeless man became the cobbler’s apprentice. That night, he slept inside a small room and not with the dog.</p>
<p>Word spread far and near, of a cobbler who sells exquisitely beautiful shoes never before seen in the kingdom.</p>
<p>Many moons passed. One morning, the apprentice was making a pair of slippers, and not fancy shoes. Simple slippers, that were fit for regular use; the kind of slippers, that was customary to be slipped onto the feet of the dead when they are put on the pyre. So the apprentice recalled from his soul ferrying days of the yamadootā. Suddenly a loud knocking on the door was heard. The king’s servants had arrived. “We want the most beautiful shoes in your inventory for the King. Bring them at once”.  The apprentice said, “My lord, all my shoes are sold. I’m making a new pair of slippers today and its almost done. Please take these slippers instead of the shoes you are looking for”. “Are you out of your mind? You will be at once taken prisoner and will be produced at the royal court”, the king’s servant thundered. Just then, a soldier on horseback arrived at the cobbler’s house. He whispered something in the royal servant’s ears. The soldier and the king’s servants left in a hurry - for the king was dead. They however, forgot to take the “dead men slippers” which the apprentice had now almost finished.</p>
<h2 id="the-wedding">The wedding</h2>
<p>Sixteen summers came to pass. There was a wedding. The rich merchant’s daughters were getting married and the cobbler was asked to produce the most exquisite collection of shoes for them. Twenty pairs each were made for the two daughters, Sukanyā and Annapoornā. The shoes were more beautiful than the rainbow and nothing like them had been seen in the entire kingdom ever, for the apprentice put his heart and soul in them, as if those were the last pairs he was making - for someone special.</p>
<p>The wedding day neared and the cobbler asked the apprentice to deliver the shoes. On the wedding day, the apprentice arrived at the merchant’s house. The merchant’s beautiful daughters Sukanyā and Annapoornā were overjoyed to get such lovely shoes. But the apprentice had a strange feeling. He couldn’t say what it was, but a feeling of déjà vu overtook him. When the daughters were alone, the apprentice asked, “For some strange reasons, it felt like I know you both”. The elder one said, “Oh cobbler, we are not from here. We were orphans. The kind hearted merchant and his childless wife had adopted us sixteen years ago when our mother died”.</p>
<p>The apprentice felt a strange chill up his spine, as if his soul was leaving his body. He could no longer hear the drumbeats of the arriving bridegroom’s marriage party. His eyes blurred and he faded into oblivion.</p>
<hr>
<p>“Welcome back to Yamalokā yamadootā!”, said Yamā. “Your penance is over, for you now have truly understood the purpose of God’s will and the reason I had banished you from yamalokā.” The yamadootā nodded in agreement at Dharmarāja’s feet.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>The Argumentative Indian and the Globetrotter</title>
            <link>https://arunkpatra.io/posts/2020/07/the-argumentative-indian-and-the-globetrotter/</link>
            <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://arunkpatra.io/posts/2020/07/the-argumentative-indian-and-the-globetrotter/</guid>
            <description>Flashback 2005 On a rainy August evening, an arduous four legged late night flight from Chennai, India, to San Antonio, TX USA put me on a completely new journey of my professional life. A journey that gave me opportunities to meet people from almost every culture and country. I saw, observed, heard, listened, experienced and lived an incredibly rich and diverse set of cultures. And those experiences included professionalism, work ethics, food, emotional quotient and the purpose of life from a plethora of perspectives.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="flashback-2005">Flashback 2005</h2>
<p>On a rainy August evening, an arduous four legged late night flight from Chennai, India, to San Antonio, TX USA put me on a completely new journey of my professional life. A journey that gave me opportunities to meet people from almost every culture and country. I saw, observed, heard, listened, experienced and lived an incredibly rich and diverse set of cultures. And those experiences included professionalism, work ethics, food, emotional quotient and the purpose of life from a plethora of perspectives. There&rsquo;s a little bit of everything I brought back home finally in 2012, and settled down at my new workplace in Bangalore among a league of extraordinary gentlemen and inspiring ladies.</p>
<p>This article is what I learnt about conducting oneself in a business environment, especially in the Information technology industry. I juxtapose those learnings against Indian values and the Indian way of life. I present my thoughts on how I should conduct myself at a place of business given my unique background as an Indian and as a professional - all in the context of a IT organizational setup. Wanna grab a tall coffee? Medium is just fine as well.</p>
<h2 id="the-people-i-met-and-the-little-things-they-do">The People I Met, And The Little Things They Do</h2>
<p>My work took me to some of the most powerful business houses and corporations in the world across the Americas. Largely American companies predominantly with American leadership, work ethics but with a growing percentage of Indians. I saw among many other things at the workplace, how people actually work. A task group leader is invariably someone who is fully aware of all the production processes which produce something from the production line - both software and machinery. That leader is ultimately accountable for the finished goods, its quality and its shipping date. One hand to shake and one neck to choke. The task group leader is a real and concrete role that is only donned by an expert, a leader and a very very capable worker who has usually risen up the ranks doing what his/her team currently does. It was a unique thing I saw, and it is different from other cultures and countries especially India - more on it later. But first a quick aside, into the Indian way of life in general.</p>
<h2 id="of-india-of-indians-and-the-indian-way-of-life">Of India, Of Indians And The Indian Way of Life</h2>
<p>Undoubtedly, India is one of the oldest and still surviving civilizations today. Over millennia, the Indian way of life has exhibited compassion, respect for diversity, richness of thought and an expansive world view. The very fact that we have close to twenty five different languages (and thousands of unique dialects) in as many states in the country is indicative of our maturity towards diversity. We have absolutely no problems with a different way of life from our own. It&rsquo;s been like that since millennia.</p>
<p>We have our own little ways of doing things, e.g. we are compassionate in our responses, we are elaborate in our rituals, we are very very accommodating with anyone and everyone. Sometimes, that accommodating outlook is seen as too submissive, too docile and too weak and outrightly &lsquo;un-professional&rsquo; according to certain standards foreign to our culture. But anyway, suffice is to say, there is usually a very deep and far more involved reason as why Indians do those little things - both at the workplace and beyond.</p>
<h2 id="doing-business-with-the-west">Doing Business With The West</h2>
<p>Most of IT services exported out of India is to the west and western cultures. All these cultures have their own little nuances. The French and the Dutch have their own ways of doing things like greeting someone, attending a meeting, making a point etc. The Britons and Aussies and the Americans are unique in their own ways as well. But what about Indians? Oh yeah! We gel well with everyone - we are like sugar that is soluble in any liquid, be it milk, water etc. But there might be a problem there. You just don&rsquo;t put sugar in anything and everything. Sometimes sugar is just not the thing to add. Sometimes, the unique identity of the Indian which is definitive of the Indian culture is just totally missing in a business context - and I am not even going into uniqueness of the Japanese culture. The biggest problem is that, we many a time, get things mixed up, sometimes pretty horribly - as regards our business and work etiquettes in an IT services context. I think, we have warmed up and we can cut to the chase.</p>
<h2 id="of-meetings-of-phone-calls-of-calendars-of-emails">Of Meetings, Of Phone Calls, Of Calendars, Of Emails</h2>
<p>The IT &ldquo;Service&rdquo; Industry. One should really try and understand, what we mean by service, whom are we serving(not by name, but by culture). Sometimes the meaning of &ldquo;service&rdquo; gets downgraded to such low levels that, &ldquo;yes sir&rdquo;, &ldquo;I will get it done&rdquo;, &ldquo;no problem&rdquo;, &ldquo;we will fix it&rdquo; becomes staple. So staple, that it actually looks like fodder or should is say farrago?</p>
<p>When I talk of meetings, there&rsquo;s much to learn from the west. It&rsquo;s just plain dis-respectful to slap a meeting on someone&rsquo;s calendar without any heads-up, without any agenda and without any breathing space. The explanation that &ldquo;we got a burning situation&rdquo; is so common that it sounds lame and pretty stupid. Who created the fire? Definitely not me? For me, definitely that fire is not as important as my kids and wife! It&rsquo;s my choice what I do with my time and someone even having the slightest amount of disrespect for that, is probably being totally out of line. We also have a tendency of self-inviting to meetings. It&rsquo;s like a mark of respect to call someone&rsquo;s superior to a meeting without that person neither having a takeaway nor an input to provide - sounds like plain sycophancy to me. Why am I even in this meeting? Shouldn&rsquo;t have I just declined me? Oh my Indian culture! What would the customer think? What would my boss think? I must join this midnight call - my boss and the customer will be happy. Okay! Fact is, they are not - definitely not your professional customer. They are probably intrigued at your &ldquo;yes sir&rdquo; behavior at everything - it&rsquo;s beyond their comprehension.</p>
<p>CC&rsquo;s or email carbon copies! It&rsquo;s probably one of the single most abused and misunderstood things in modern business culture. We Indian&rsquo;s have done our part to ruin it further. CC is not meant to appease a boss, it&rsquo;s not meant to threaten someone. It&rsquo;s meant to keep someone informed only when it&rsquo;s important(and the CC&rsquo;d person actually needs that piece of information) for someone. Your American counterpart will probably be upset with too many emails which don&rsquo;t even need any attention from him/her - it&rsquo;s just distracting them.</p>
<p>Phone calls! What&rsquo;s the time right now? Can&rsquo;t it wait? Whom am I calling? I can call my mommy anytime. My mommy can call me anytime. Are you my mommy? I got only one, and I am sure about that. If I can&rsquo;t respect someone&rsquo;s personal time, that&rsquo;s just plain disrespectful. Plan better. If it&rsquo;s an emergency, text. Don&rsquo;t barge in. The one you are calling has probably never sold his/her personal time/life for a salary. BTW, why do I even have the need of those uncomfortable silences in a call? How do I make the phone call as pleasant as possible? &ldquo;Hey Billy, how are the Spurs doing?&rdquo;. Billy is my customer, from San Antonio, TX, a great NBA fan and has very good taste in beer. I have never met him personally but we both have a level of respect for each other that&rsquo;s way beyond work.</p>
<p>Calendars! Am I considerate of the fact that someone has back to back meetings? How much breathing space actually one need? Did you check their vacation plan before slapping that meeting on their calendar? What&rsquo;s their work hours? It&rsquo;s just plain disrespectful and outrightly dumb to pollute someone&rsquo;s calendar with inconsiderate requests. Instead, plan better.</p>
<p>Of emails! Whom I am emailing? My boss, my CEO, my colleague, a customer, a vendor or my mom? Do I know his/her culture? Do I know how do they perceive my salutation and way of discussing the topic which I conveyed in the email. The Britons are profoundly distinct from the Americans as regards professional verbiage. The Japanese are extremely unique too. Was I considerate of their culture and especially considerate of him/her as a person. Have I invested time and effort to know cultures and people? I&rsquo;m not talking of &ldquo;eloquent english&rdquo; in emails - that&rsquo;s not even the point. But you get my drift.</p>
<h2 id="a-lot-to-learn-a-lot-to-give">A Lot To Learn, A Lot To Give</h2>
<p>We Indian&rsquo;s are unique in our ways of doing things, and it takes much much more than a few pages to present that. A couple books are also not enough. But I am not defending some of our sloppy ways of doing things when looked through a western lens. I personally have tried spreading awareness of Indian culture, Indian values and Indian history with almost all my western friends(most are also my customers). They are genuinely amazed and are so eager to know more. They tend to develop a remarkable amount of respect for us. Isn&rsquo;t it also just right for us Indians to do business with them (and hence with our own colleagues in India) in a way that they will truly appreciate? Shouldn&rsquo;t we learn?</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>I have been extremely fortunate to have landed up in a league of extraordinary gentlemen and inspiring ladies that I talked about earlier. My ex-boss and a great leader, lived, professed and taught by example as how to conduct business - and it starts with your own team in India. The small things(which go a long way), letting someone know that you are late to a meeting, letting people know upfront why you had to call so late, explaining someone why are they not needed in a meeting, the &ldquo;reassuring&rdquo; way of saying &ldquo;NO&rdquo; are something that I got to learn, right here in India and from Indians. My American friends and America embraced me into their culture and I never had the need of becoming an American (fake accent included). I think, I got a lot from everyone, and I gave back as well. Would you think if everybody starts putting in a bit more effort, the Indian service industry&rsquo;s offshore workplaces would become even more enjoyable? Let me know. And, thanks for reading!</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>The Architect</title>
            <link>https://arunkpatra.io/posts/2020/07/the-architect/</link>
            <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://arunkpatra.io/posts/2020/07/the-architect/</guid>
            <description>Image © Warner Bros. Pictures, Village Roadshow Pictures
  Who are you? So asked Neo Contrary to what many might think, the Information Technology shop floor is not vastly different from a production line of the manufacturing industry. There are stark similarities. Same things in IT as well; sales, marketing, planning, design, processes, technology, products and people who create those products - in this case, software.
It is but natural to think, that in the IT industry as well, there are many different roles that people play in the shop floor.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<figure><img src="/img/the-architect-masthead-1280x640.png"
         alt="The Architect"/><figcaption>
            <p>Image © Warner Bros. Pictures, Village Roadshow Pictures</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<h2 id="who-are-you-so-asked-neo">Who are you? So asked Neo</h2>
<p>Contrary to what many might think, the Information Technology shop floor is not vastly different from a production line of the manufacturing industry. There are stark similarities. Same things in IT as well; sales, marketing, planning, design, processes, technology, products and people who create those products - in this case, software.</p>
<p>It is but natural to think, that in the IT industry as well, there are many different roles that people play in the shop floor. I discuss one such role in this article - the role of the Architect. I present some thoughts of my own as well.</p>
<h2 id="gandalf-the-gray">Gandalf the Gray</h2>
<p>
    <img src="/img/software-architect-gandalf.jpg"  alt="Gandalf"  class="left"  style="float:left; margin-right:15px; margin-top:5px "  />

 Remember Gandalf, old guy with the pointy hat? If that rings any bells, it  also reminds one, of Frodo of the Shire and Aragorn son of Arathorn; all mighty heroes in a great endeavor. But Gandalf, as you might agree, was the master planner, adept at everything. The pitch, the motivation, the planning, the leadership, the tactics, the craft, the wisdom, the expertise with the sword and hand to hand combat. He had it all. He was the single most important character in the endeavor without whom, chances were high that the fellowship would have failed. He was the one true Architect of Middle Earth. J. R. R. Tolkien’s cell phone is unreachable since quite sometime, else I would have given him a call for a discussion on the topic.</p>
<p>So, is a Software Architect(and they go by many names - more on it later) the one who knows everything about building and delivering software? Is the Architect an old grumpy guy with strange semblances with a professor with a minimum of twenty years of IT experience? Far from the truth. Let’s see why.</p>
<h2 id="its-not-the-years-honey-its-the-mileage">It’s not the years honey, it&rsquo;s the mileage</h2>
<p>There is no book ever published, no online or offline course ever offered that can make an Architect out of someone. Now that’s a tall claim! I’m sure, there are a bunch of certifying agencies out there, looking for my blood right now. But that’s ok. Now, all those books and content, can definitely impart certain skills and share some established point of views, but they can only do so much. So how does someone become an architect, what is an architect’s real job and what is an architect’s real value in the modern Information Technology industry? But first a quick aside into human psychology.</p>
<h2 id="dont-go-near-the-fireplace-you-will-hurt-yourself">Don’t go near the fireplace, you will hurt yourself</h2>
<p>Have you ever seen a kid heeding that advice? Well they just might, but in their heart of hearts, they secretly desire to actually touch the fireplace. But why? Well, I guess humans are wired that way. They are curious, and they are still curios even after knowing that curiosity killed the crow. Curiosity actually is the single most important thing for humans as a species.</p>
<p>But as we grow up, our curiosity gives way to different ways of life, character, our unique styles if you will. We do certain things and behave only in certain ways that have been conditioned by society, our workplace and the like. Fact is, no one likes to be told what is good or bad, what one should do and should not. People just hate it. Well we might agree with our boss or the project sponsor, but we really don’t like it too much. A certain kind of skill(which is not found in books usually) is required to sell advice, it’s a subtle art. But beware, advice given for free, especially upfront when someone’s tail is not on fire yet, is usually ignored. Let it be the software developer, the project manager, the sponsor or the customer. That subtle art, backed by breadth and depth of knowledge, honed by empathy, polished by rational and perfected with professionalism is the most important skill of an architect.</p>
<p>A developer starts with a computer, codes a few simple programs, moves into designing and coding yet more complex programs. Soon, that leads to designing larger and larger systems. That gives way to making long lasting decisions that can make or break an entire organization. And a stage comes when that young coder turns into a master planner, who sees the entire technology world and business world as one large continuous canvas. He/she has the onerous responsibility and the power of making decisions that can change human lives. That is the path an architect’s life traces. Each of these stages is built upon the previous one, brick upon brick. There can never be a roof without the walls. No wall without a foundation. Each stage creates wisdom and learning. And it’s really hard to disseminate that wisdom to anyone and everyone in a way that makes sense for them. And this is one of the most important jobs and duties of a successful architect - communication.</p>
<h2 id="communication-is-key">Communication is key</h2>
<p>Communication is not just transmission of words over sound waves. It’s not what we have to say, or what we say. It’s all about how the listener on the other end perceives. Did it have the intended effect? Was it convincing? Was it backed by facts, presented coherently and explained to an extent that was needed? Lectures, architectural diagrams, documents, flow charts and presentations are meaningless if the listener or the reader was not convinced.</p>
<p>I know an eight year old kid who once showed up at a lecture on the Theory of Relativity and asked so profound a question, that the professor was compelled to come running to the parking lot looking for the kid. In the IT industry also, different stakeholders understand remarkably different languages, have remarkably different backgrounds and remarkably different attention spans. It’s an architect’s job to ensure that he/she has the skills to deal with all of them successfully.</p>
<h2 id="looking-into-the-crystal-ball">Looking into the crystal ball</h2>
<p>One can truly understand the present if one knows what has come to pass. The ability of looking into the future, is the next level of mastery which an architect aspires to acquire. What is going to be the result of a choice we make today? How will technology evolve, and more importantly how market dynamics and consumer sentiments will shape the nature of businesses, business models and hence the fabric of technology solutions. One can’t truly claim to be an architect who can not see into the future of a project or product. Sometimes that deep gaze of the architect must peer through a decade into the future. Needless to say, the right way to acquire such telescopic vision is constant learning, not just technology learning but everything that has a bearing on end users of a technology backed service, people who build those services/products and the way today’s business world runs.</p>
<h2 id="technology-is-commodity-rationale-is-not">Technology is commodity, rationale is not</h2>
<p>The technology world, especially software is evolving so fast that no institute of higher education in Information Technology can keep pace. In my opinion, it’s the fundamentals of computing, clarity of thought, decision making process, creativity and nurturing of ideas that must be focussed upon, in educational institutions. In my opinion, an educational institution offering courses on Information Technology and teaching Java, HTML, Javascript, PL/SQL, Cloud and Big Data is doing a grave injustice to students and to the society. An active encouragement to become bold adventures, passionate learners and creative thinkers will do sustainable good to the society.</p>
<p>A deeper focus on driving decisions based on rational thinking and argued based on wisdom is probably the real job of an architect. It’s hard work for an architect to acquire such skills. It needs excellent mentors and a voracious appetite of reading.</p>
<h2 id="the-classifications-and-the-jargon">The classifications and the jargon</h2>
<p>There are so many different areas of specialization and classifications for architects. It’s good to know but then the world wide web is your better source of information. But suffice is to say, the enterprise architect, the solution architect, the technical architect, the application architect, the information architect, the data architect and the security architect are all real and valid roles with varying degrees of focus on different areas. But the cross cutting concern remains, rationale thinking, exemplary communication skills, deep understanding of human dynamics, an expansive breadth of knowledge and an insatiable desire of knowledge.</p>
<h2 id="the-conclusion">The Conclusion</h2>
<p>If one aspires to choose an architect’s profession, I would say, it’s a rewarding and humbling experience at the same time. It’s a very important role which rolls up leadership, knowledge, humility, curiosity and empathy into one single role - the role of an Architect.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Building a Product Development Team</title>
            <link>https://arunkpatra.io/posts/2020/06/building-a-product-development-team/</link>
            <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://arunkpatra.io/posts/2020/06/building-a-product-development-team/</guid>
            <description>Introduction Not every problem can be solved using software, but in today&amp;rsquo;s Digital age, probably every single modern service is being enabled by technology and implemented to a good extent in software.
What is a Product? A product is a physical realization of a business idea. It&amp;rsquo;s a concrete tool that helps solve a problem. Building a successful product, whether it&amp;rsquo;s a product developed using Information Technology/Software or not, is easier said than done.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>
<p>Not every problem can be solved using software, but in today&rsquo;s Digital age, probably every single modern service is
being enabled by technology and implemented to a good extent in software.</p>
<p>What is a Product? A product is a physical realization of a business idea. It&rsquo;s a concrete tool that helps solve a
problem. Building a successful product, whether it&rsquo;s a product developed using Information Technology/Software or not,
is easier said than done. According to studies, around 70 - 90% new products fail. The percentage goes as high as 95%
in some cases.</p>
<p>In this article, we discuss, what I think, could be done to increase our chances of success while building new software
powered products. Specifically, I focus on how to <em>build an ace product development team that&rsquo;s second to none</em>. But first,
let&rsquo;s warm up a bit, just a bit, and then we cut to the chase.</p>
<h2 id="the-a-team---whats-the-motivation">The A++ Team - What&rsquo;s the motivation?</h2>
<p>It&rsquo;s not just about the business idea, the novelty factor, the target market, the sales and marketing plan, the
million/billion dollar funding, the sleek design, or the cool UI. None of these alone can ever guarantee success of a
product. It&rsquo;s a combination of many of these ingredients and many more ingredients that can make the secret sauce for
success. One of those key ingredients is the <em>Team</em>. And the team needs just one single thing to start in a 100%
supercharged way. That thing is called &ldquo;belief&rdquo;. (And believe me - because its almost unbelievable - it&rsquo;s not just the
technical skills that one needs to be successful and create awesome things.) They need to believe that, they are the
ones who would be changing the world with the product they build. If the team does not &ldquo;believe&rdquo; 100% in the idea, if
they are not sold into it and don&rsquo;t relate to it at a level beyond renumeration, chances are high you are never going
to build your A++ team. The investor/sponsor funds the project if he/she believes that he/she can make money. The team
builds the best of the best when they believe that it&rsquo;s their own baby and then it becomes a labor of love. How many of
you would agree? Please let me know in the comments.</p>
<h2 id="the-method-to-the-madness">The Method to the Madness</h2>
<p>Software product development is part science and part art. There are specific job titles available for people who are
skilled in the art of software product development. But believe me or not, you probably don&rsquo;t need any of those
experts(they might help a lot though and one should use them by all means). All that you need is the sponsor&rsquo;s skin in
the game, a compelling business case, a market to sell, a clear head to think, a methodical approach,
immense-immense-immense focus, a supercharged team, transparency, clear communications and an unassailable desire to
succeed.</p>
<p>So let&rsquo;s cut to the chase and focus on how do we create the A++ product development dream team of ours.</p>
<h2 id="what-do-i-need-to-build-a-team---the-first-team-member">What do I need to Build a Team - The first Team Member</h2>
<p>So you want your A++ team hunh? What do you need to start? People obviously. Isn&rsquo;t it? Wrong. Not just any people. We
need the sharpest and the brightest. Wrong again. Ok, we need the MIT undergrad and the Wharton MBA(I have the greatest
respect for MIT, Wharton and the incredibly amazing people over there). Wrong again. Ok, we need the &ldquo;Product Manager&rdquo;
and the &ldquo;Product Design Head&rdquo; from the XYZ company with 15 years of experience. Wrong again. Ok, a task master who can
get things done. Wrong. Ok then, we need change agents, disruptors, transformation champions, rainmakers!
Ok, I give up&hellip;</p>
<p>You need, a leader to start with - and leader is not a designation. You need someone who has lived life in a pretty
wholesome way. Someone who has seen some hardships in life, dejections, failures and successes and has tons of common
sense and ready wit. You need someone, well travelled, well read(not just technical qualification, programming
languages, frameworks, agile, scrum, cloud services and the latest and greatest from the silicon valley). You need
someone who doesn&rsquo;t hesitate to laugh and cry with someone totally unknown. Someone who is a great human being, a
common man/woman with a huge heart. A good speaker, but an even better listener. Yes, that&rsquo;s exactly what you need to
start building your A++ software development team(No, I didn&rsquo;t have an overdose of those The Expendables movies during
the lockdown - I&rsquo;m talking for real, from my own experiences). There are a few other nice to have qualities of this
person, but that&rsquo;s ok.</p>
<h2 id="building-your-team---further">Building your Team - Further</h2>
<p>Ok, now you hired the leader. Remember you(the sponsor) hired him/her. Now trust him/her. Give him/her the freedom,
the freedom to build the team they see fit. Enable and empower the leader with all the right tools and resources.
These tools and resources also include mentoring and coaching as the need may be. You as a leader of the leader now
needs to take a backseat, kind of always there in the background but not hovering like a chopper either. You are the
leader&rsquo;s safety net, you are the Plan B.</p>
<p>Now, comes the good stuff. The team. Should I hire just anyone? Well, it depends. Your needs of product development
might require some unique skills in specific technologies or specific arts. You absolutely need to look for them. A
carpenter possibly can&rsquo;t be hired to do the job of a graphic designer. But if a carpenter does apply for the job, who
produces the world&rsquo;s most beautiful, simplest and most functional chairs, I can guarantee you, you would benefit from
giving the carpenter a long hard look. It would be worth the effort. In essence, it&rsquo;s not just what someone knows, but
what someone can learn and is bringing in. How creative is the person, how positive someone&rsquo;s attitude towards life is.
How far one is ready to go to achieve success and what is the very meaning of success for that person. If you think,
that this person can change the world along with you, you got your A+++ player(Just like in the movie Kungfu Panda. A
big fat panda can become THE big fat panda - the Dragon Warrior. All that is needed is belief, just as Master Oogway
said and Master Shifu believed). Remember, you yourself are a A++ player. Just about anyone with the right coaching,
right mentoring and right tools can become an A player - they just need to believe in themselves. It must become a part
of their psychology, &ldquo;What one man/woman can do, another definitely can&rdquo;. I am definitely not saying that one can
become Steve Jobs or Elon Musk - one doesn&rsquo;t need to. But one can definitely change the world in even better ways than
Steve and Elon.</p>
<p>A more grounded reality is however, go for the very best talent that you think that works for you. Keep an eye on the
timelines of your project - you get my drift. And yes, one more thing. The more diverse the team is, the better.
Diversity in terms of language, culture, demography, sexual orientation, color, political inclination just helps, not
hurts. You are the best decider for yourself based on real project needs on the ground.</p>
<h2 id="the-big-guns-the-ammo---the-tools">The Big Guns, the Ammo - The Tools</h2>
<p>Ok, the motivation from the sponsor, the true leader and a team that believes, have now been hired. We need something
else. We don&rsquo;t go out fighting a tactical war against a sophisticated adversary with primitive, crude weapons with belief
bursting out of our hearts. That would be suicide. We need the right tools. You as a leader, got to enable your
software product development team with the right tools. But even before that, talk to the team, understand how they do
what they do. Observe, just don&rsquo;t speak, observe from a distance - as if you are the learner. Over time, you would know
what problems they face, practical problems. Now go hunting for tools. The very best
IDE(Integrated Development Environment), the very best collaboration tools, the very best automation tools, the
largest box the developers need to run the CI builds, the most robust and most stable tools if you will. So, that the
team can just code, and code happily. Do not, I repeat, do not cut corners with the developers and their tools. Listen
to every demand(whether you understand fully or not) and take your time to understand first and then decide on the
investment. Tools are the very first enablers of success for your A Team.</p>
<h2 id="the-clarity-the-plan-the-open-lines-of-communication">The Clarity, The Plan, The Open Lines of Communication</h2>
<p>Nobody wants a haphazard plan. Nobody likes a moving target to chase. But honestly if it&rsquo;s a moving target after all,
at least everyone in the team must know and be prepared for that. You can call it agility or whatever you like, but you
just can&rsquo;t assume that everyone is fine with your demands. The team must be an equal shareholder in every decision that
is made in the team from day zero.</p>
<p>Over time, and after the initial hustle and bustle and whirlwind activity, you will see patterns evolving in the team.
You as a leader will become richer as well in your own thought process. You will be able to sharpen the plan. Don&rsquo;t
forget the sponsor either, he/she also needs to be a part of the communication chain. Oh please, I am not talking about
status reports - they are so passé. I am talking of enabling the sponsor with the right tools so that he/she can become
an extension to the development team. Yes its possible with today&rsquo;s modern tools.</p>
<h2 id="of-plans-gone-wrong-of-humans-of-empathy-of-fear-and-hope">Of Plans Gone Wrong, Of Humans, Of Empathy, Of Fear and Hope</h2>
<p>I am a human being. I have so many different organs in my body. When a specific organ is not so well, I take extra care
of it, I see a doctor and the like. I do that voluntarily. Why should it be any different with your software product
development team? Didn&rsquo;t they sign up with you and bought your pitch that they are going to change the world? You
filled their minds with dreams, hope and ambition. Now is the time to fulfill your oaths as a leader. And there is no
better time to prove yourself as a leader than when things go wrong, horribly wrong. Here&rsquo;s the leader&rsquo;s golden chance
to use this very difficult moment to strengthen the team even more - from within. Sweet! You do this as a leader,
leading by example, by sharing the load, by taking the bullet for your team, by doubling down on your own efforts.
You, lead in the true sense. You become more creative, get all the help you can from others, and make that help
available to the team. You introspect, listen more and replan as needed. Sometimes, you take a short pause and go
hang out at the bar or see a football game with the team.</p>
<h2 id="concrete-plans">Concrete Plans</h2>
<p>Think deep, look into the future, plan big, but start small. Baby steps are always good, a 100 day plan is excellent.
Foster a culture of refactoring code, reinventing and readjusting as needed. It should become second nature, all made
easy by the use of tools. Convince your team, that there&rsquo;s no such thing called bad decisions or bad code, its just
that they did not see everything coming. Show them what happens if code is written in a particular way and what impact
it has on the success chances of a project. Believe me, all the great individuals you hired in the team, will overnight
clean up the code and make it better, much much better.</p>
<p>So, plan well, get the buy-in from the sponsor, get it signed off by the developers as well, and move with confidence,
without the fear of failure. Failure is just another name for experience. But life is short, and we don&rsquo;t have the time
to commit all the mistakes ourselves. So learn from other&rsquo;s mistakes. We got a 100 day plan, remember?</p>
<h2 id="a-note-to-the-product-developer">A Note to The Product Developer</h2>
<p>I myself, as a developer know that, it always helps to work incrementally. Commit your code often, maintain a code
coverage of greater than 80%, document your code as if you are waxing your new car, be fair with your fellow
developers, not only help, but find opportunities to help your fellow team members. Automate, automate and automate.
Use tools to communicate, collaborate and share. Replace any and every repetitive task with an automated process.
Believe me, you will code with joy. You will have more spare time. You will love to code, and you will see the most
awesome product shaping up - right in front of your eyes. You will have the best and most memorable time of your
lives - and you will not even regret if we fail. Success will follow.</p>
<h2 id="the-conclusion">The Conclusion</h2>
<p>A successful product development team can be built - it&rsquo;s hard, but it can be done. What&rsquo;s needed is the business case,
the market, right motivation, the right mindset, an understanding of human dynamics, tools and a lot of common sense.
I have failed more often than have I succeeded. But with each failure, and after working with each individual, my
team&rsquo;s success rate and hence my own success rate, has just increased. And it has happened by leaps and bounds.</p>
<p>I think, I am looking at the next great leader and successful product development team - I am looking at you.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Online Certifications</title>
            <link>https://arunkpatra.io/posts/2020/06/online-certifications/</link>
            <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://arunkpatra.io/posts/2020/06/online-certifications/</guid>
            <description>The E-Learning and Online Technical Certification Market According to Global Market Insights, the e-Learning market size crossed the USD 200 billion mark in 2019 and is expected to grow at over 8% between 2020 and 2026. This data appears to be pre-Covid19 projections. It&amp;rsquo;s not at all difficult to see that the growth rate of this market is definitely going to go north in the current situations. Its just safe to say for now, that e-learning and online technical certification market is booming and will continue to expand rapidly if not explode altogether.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="the-e-learning-and-online-technical-certification-market">The E-Learning and Online Technical Certification Market</h2>
<p>According to Global Market Insights, the e-Learning market size crossed the USD 200 billion mark in 2019 and is
expected to grow at over 8% between 2020 and 2026. This data appears to be pre-Covid19 projections. It&rsquo;s not at all
difficult to see that the growth rate of this market is definitely going to go north in the current situations. Its
just safe to say for now, that e-learning and online technical certification market is booming and will continue to
expand rapidly if not explode altogether.</p>
<h2 id="what-is-learning-and-what-should-it-mean-in-the-true-sense">What is learning, and what should it mean in the true sense?</h2>
<p>Learning is the acquisition of the art, some form of skill which enables us to do something useful, e.g. earn a living,
defeat an adversary etc. Another definition could be, &ldquo;learning is transfer of experience from the teacher to the
student&rdquo;. Over millennia, learning has also become a burgeoning business. In ancient India, this business involved a
one time fee known as &ldquo;guru-dakshina&rdquo; that was payable to the teacher by the student upon demand, any time after
graduation from the institute. The condition however was that, the teacher was entitled to ask any &ldquo;guru-dakshina&rdquo;
they saw fit. The demand of payment could not be countered or negotiated in any way whatsoever and non-payment was a
severe offense and actually unheard of in ancient India. The &ldquo;guru&rdquo; or the teacher was more powerful than the king of
the land and had complete immunity from any prosecution from the government. The model worked for millennia and by
around 1000 AD, India was the most advanced country in the world according to all known and recorded history - in the
field of fundamental sciences, mathematics, astronomy, medicine, government and governance, accounting practices,
warfare, spiritualism, art, literature and music. India had the lion&rsquo;s share of the global economy. In essence, the
education system was a proven model that was a major contributor to India&rsquo;s success story till around 1000 AD. So, is
it safe to say that, education itself, the purpose of education, and the way education is imparted should never ever
be put into the hands of &ldquo;just business, driven by the only goal of capital generation in open markets&rdquo;? I would let
you decide for yourself. I however believe, societies and civilizations where the true meaning of education is
understood, and teachers/learning institutions are given the highest respect, are the ones which produce sustainable
development and growth of the human race.</p>
<h2 id="modern-education-systems">Modern Education Systems</h2>
<p>Evolution is the law of nature. The weak perish, the best genes survive and multiply and move ahead. However this does
not mean that the human race or for that matter any species, just becomes better and better. It is well documented in
the literature that all advanced civilizations have a tendency to self-destruct. Why this happens, is not the matter
of discussion in this article. So, moving on. The objective of education also has changed over time. From survival and
the pursuit of art, it has graduated to different forms like developing weapons of mass destruction. Yet another goal
is to transfer dollars, sometimes unthinkable large amounts of monies from a student&rsquo;s pocket to a businessman&rsquo;s pocket
who is not even remotely concerned about the meaning of education and all the stuff we talked about in the prior
sections of this post. But anyway, modern education systems and education delivery media and the business of education
have successfully worked till modern times. I fancy thinking, that timeframe to be somewhere around the turn of this
century? More and more people got educated and created wonderful things for mankind, our health improved, flow of money
became better and the like. Life was good.</p>
<h2 id="the-start-of-the-degenerative-phase">The Start Of The Degenerative Phase</h2>
<p>The degeneration of the education system was a global phenomenon. There was no country in the modern(capitalist) world
that remained untouched - or should I say, the virus with no name just spread without a cure. Population exploded, and
so did the education market. Aahaa! Here&rsquo;s is a market that is screaming out to be mined! So where there is nectar,
can the honey bee be far behind. These honey bees came in droves, wearing expensive suits, and ties(I also have suits
and ties that I use occasionally depending on the need) and opened up shop. Educational institutions mushroomed - they
promised jobs too. The financial markets lined up their sharpest salesmen to dole out large student loans - without
even thinking twice. I was appalled to see a student pursuing medicine in Louisville, KY who had taken a $80,000
student loan. One evening I sat with him and asked, &ldquo;have you done the math&rdquo;? He said, &ldquo;I don&rsquo;t care much&hellip; I will pay
it out over time. And even if I can&rsquo;t, I don&rsquo;t care too much either&rdquo;. I expressed a deep sigh of utter pain and
walked out. The reader probably knows already what the $80,000 student loan for a 23 year old medical student in
today&rsquo;s times means and what it actually entails for the next 20 years. The essence is, the once pious world of
education was attacked by a virus, and the virus wore suits and the objective of that virus was to make
money(even more money, at an ever increasing rate) without any other concern whatsoever - we are a capitalistic world
after all, remember?</p>
<h2 id="new-italian-suits">New Italian Suits</h2>
<p>Italian suits are good, I have one(however, they are totally inapplicable for the Indian climate, I live and work in
India) and nothing wrong with them. But I guess you get my drift. The education and learning business constantly
re-invented itself, made possible by the brightest MBA&rsquo;s all over the world ever ready to go for the kill. In the long,
cold, stone walled corridors of modern businesses and corporations, it was decided that, we need to deliver learning
through new digital media. Excellent! That&rsquo;s awesome, so much greenhouse gas can be thus eliminated. I am all in for
that. This is awesome. Now even someone in the remotest part of the world can get access to quality education easily
and in an affordable way - all made possible by the power of Digital. It can&rsquo;t get any better. However a strange thing
happened. This noble thought and innovative way of making education accessible and cheap, gave way to something else.
Next section please.</p>
<h2 id="technology-corporations-individuals-and-open-source">Technology, Corporations, Individuals and Open Source</h2>
<p>Let&rsquo;s take a step back. Give me five more minutes please. Let&rsquo;s now shift our focus to a specific domain, the technology domain. More specifically, the information technology/software domain. This domain is unique in many ways. Technologies, software and frameworks are created at a whirlwind pace today. There are so many wonderful intellectuals, coders, and common people who create marvelous pieces of software that have the capacity to change the world. The world will always remember Open Source and Linus Torvalds - I am not associated with Linus in any way. Modern and large technology corporations are doing their bit by constantly inventing technology that have the power to change the world. They thus need to be thanked for the effort they are taking. So far so good. Life is good, and everybody did their part - hopefully in the right earnest.</p>
<h2 id="people-need-jobs">People Need Jobs</h2>
<p>Millions of knowledge workers are needing jobs, technology jobs. They apply for jobs, get hired. They apply again for a next job and get hired and so on. The technology market (driven by business needs) is so crowded, that if I don&rsquo;t know the latest and greatest tech, the current lingo, we can&rsquo;t get an interview, forget about getting a job. Even if one knows the tech, the latest and greatest, chances are you won&rsquo;t get a job. You need something else.</p>
<h2 id="a-piece-of-paper---with-a-stamp-of-approval---from-the-guy-with-a-tie">A Piece of Paper - With a Stamp of Approval - From the Guy with a Tie</h2>
<p>Hmmm, I guess I am reaching towards the closing part of my article now. The world seeks validation, the world needs validation. The graduate was given a piece of paper when he/she graduated from the university. That was a necessary document. It was issued by a University, bound by solemn oath to do good for the society. It&rsquo;s another matter altogether whether the true value of education was imparted or not. Life has come full circle for the graduate again. Today, he/she needs a piece of paper again, a certificate, issued by someone who I trust(blindly??? arghhh..) that says, I am skilled in a certain technology or competency or a cloud/technology service sold by a large technology company. That piece of paper is issued through the familiar process called certification. Ummmm, sounds fair enough. That would kind of serve the same purpose the graduate&rsquo;s degree served, right? Well, there&rsquo;s the interesting part and the conclusion of my article.</p>
<h2 id="why-why-on-gods-green-earth">Why? Why on God&rsquo;s Green Earth?</h2>
<p>Money is a piece of paper. It can give someone food, health and power. It can kill billions, it can do every conceivable form of bad and good as well. Money is a scarce resource, it should be conserved(no, all of a sudden I have not become anti-business and I don&rsquo;t need a Harvard degree to understand micro and macro economics - common sense prevails again). Just like money, time is scare. Time should be invested in my opinion to do good for ourselves and good for others in a meaningful and sustainable way. Time spent in doing something to fill the coffers of the Italian suit guy(suit or no suit does not matter) in exchange of a piece of paper is something I personally am not able to comprehend fully - I have fairly average IQ, but I can guarantee I am not dumb. &ldquo;So, what are you saying Arun? Are you saying, no one should do certifications after all?&rdquo;. I ain&rsquo;t saying nothing. I would let the reader answer that question for themselves and do whatever is best for them. I am no one to put words in anyone&rsquo;s mouth. I am neither a sorcerer, nor a paid columnist, nor Steve Jobs adept at creating a &ldquo;reality distortion field&rdquo;. I am a common and humble human being fueled by the desire to pursue truth, do the right thing and spread awareness - that is both my dharma and karma.</p>
<h2 id="so-what-should-one-do-how-to-get-a-job-after-all">So What Should One Do? How to get a Job after all?</h2>
<p>&ldquo;Ok, ok, ok, Arun, I heard you. You are not totally insane but not making full sense either. Please tell me how to get a job and who is going to believe that I have actually acquired these ten skills which the employer is looking for. Tell me how do I prove my credibility to the employer&rdquo;. Creativity my friend! And while being creative, also do a ton of good to humanity. Be smart, save money, change the world. &ldquo;Come again?&rdquo;. Go ahead and start an open source project, or better even join an open source project. Contribute with your best possible capacity. Let your name show up in the release notes. The entire world will see, what you know, what you did and what everybody in the community thinks about you - your open source project had probably the wisest, nicest and most civilized guys bound by extremely high code of conduct. Let your work validate your skills and your credibility, which is probably without doubt, a far more convincing medium than a piece of paper. Sounds good? &ldquo;What else?&rdquo;, Head over to the developer boards, answer as many questions as you can. People will see you, know you and thank you. You will be doing your bit to change the world. &ldquo;But I don&rsquo;t have the skills to start with, and that&rsquo;s the original intent of certification&rdquo;. You can still learn, and actually not pay the guy with the tie. You can learn great coding skills and specific technologies by looking at great code. Just ask for help, even if you are a rookie, people will point you in the right direction - that&rsquo;s the code of conduct that Open Source is bound by. &ldquo;And what about technology sold by large technology companies and tech that is proprietary? They say that the training and certification is only available from their learning portal&rdquo; My friend, spend a good weekend going through the docs. 90% of tech today (tech that actually matters) is open source and rarely one charges to read their documentation - at a maximum they will ask you to create an user ID on their platform. Go ahead and try, learn it, by doing it. Create something fresh, collaborate with someone and give back to the world. You will get hired, because the employer is smart - usually much smarter than the job seeker.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>It&rsquo;s not about the hurdles. They will always be there. It&rsquo;s all about the intent. If the intent is to do good to ourselves and to others in a meaningful and sustainable way, we will always do the right thing, and we ourselves will find out innovative ways to do our bit of good.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Choosing a Public Cloud Platform</title>
            <link>https://arunkpatra.io/posts/2020/06/choosing-a-public-cloud-platform/</link>
            <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://arunkpatra.io/posts/2020/06/choosing-a-public-cloud-platform/</guid>
            <description>Do I know why and if I need Cloud? I recently heard a statement from someone in the IT industry saying &amp;ldquo;We got to do cloud, cloud is everything&amp;rdquo;. When probed why, the answer came in - &amp;ldquo;Arun, you need to update yourself. Don&amp;rsquo;t you know that everybody has adopted it and didn&amp;rsquo;t you see the hype curve?&amp;rdquo;. I repeated politely, &amp;ldquo;Still my question&amp;rdquo;. Pat came the answer, &amp;ldquo;Please talk to the engineering team&amp;rdquo;.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="do-i-know-why-and-if-i-need-cloud">Do I know why and if I need Cloud?</h2>
<p>I recently heard a statement from someone in the IT industry saying &ldquo;We got to do cloud, cloud is everything&rdquo;.
When probed why, the answer came in - &ldquo;Arun, you need to update yourself. Don&rsquo;t you know that everybody has adopted it
and didn&rsquo;t you see the hype curve?&rdquo;. I repeated politely, &ldquo;Still my question&rdquo;. Pat came the answer, &ldquo;Please talk to the
engineering team&rdquo;. I walked away muttering, &ldquo;Okay, I think I know what you mean&rdquo;.</p>
<p>I would think, that unless I understand fully my workload and what type of services those workloads need, and what pain
I would be solving by using PaaS or IaaS, I am not ready yet to make a decision - I am just not qualified yet! I also
need to know what are my scalability, availability and reliability needs. If I do not understand these terms, I am not
qualified to make my decision - the decision would most likely be a bad one. I also need to think from the perspective
of operations and monitoring, logging, continuous deployment, rolling updates and painless rollbacks. If I do not
understand these terms and don&rsquo;t yet understand as how far these aspects go towards total cost of ownership and
business agility, I would most probably be digging a grave for myself by making a wrong decision. In essence, I must
ask all the right questions. The answers are only meaningful if the questions are relevant and contextual to my
workloads, for now and for the foreseeable shelf life of the software - not those questions and fancy terms that the
cloud sales guys and marketing brochures listed. However, more often than not, brochures are an excellent source
of great information to start with.</p>
<h2 id="what-i-need-vs-what-the-cloud-provider-is-selling">What I need v/s what the cloud provider is selling?</h2>
<p>Do I know what are the top three priorities for my application/system? In the sales pitch, the sales guy listed two
dozen services and took all the contacts from me of my IT decision makers working with different technologies who are
trying to solve different problems. His only goal was sales, sales and sales(and one should be totally fine with
that - that&rsquo;s the primary job of the sales team after all). &ldquo;But what about me? What about my developer who is facing
some real issues - this service is just not fit for my needs, and the weekly status call is not helping much.&rdquo; This
happened to me. There was another provider, whose sales guy told me this after seeing my demo - &ldquo;Arun, honestly, you
are using a very expensive service of ours and you can very easily meet your application needs by using a far cheaper
and far simpler service, go ahead and try that.&rdquo; I said - &ldquo;God bless you - you are a gentleman&rdquo;. Yet another provider
asked me rather bluntly, &ldquo;How tightly is your application coupled with our services?&rdquo;. Promptly I replied,
&ldquo;errr&hellip; actually my app is very tightly coupled with your services&rdquo;&hellip; What I did not tell them, was &ldquo;Please stop
looking at me as if I am an imbecile, you are actually painting a very bad picture of yourself&rdquo;.</p>
<h2 id="how-mature-is-the-service-again">How mature is the service again?</h2>
<p>Is the service I am wanting to use GA or is it a beta/preview release which the cloud provider is essentially
providing to use for free (BTW, there&rsquo;s nothing called a free lunch)? Such a provider is probably gathering very
valuable usage data, error log data, crash reports from me to improve their own product - and they had mentioned
this in the fine print, which you agreed to. However they probably don&rsquo;t worry much at the beta/preview stage as
what pothole you hit by using a beta product(that&rsquo;s the very definition of beta?) - that can severely hurt developer
morale sometimes though. Among the top public cloud providers, there is one who rarely releases any beta/preview
service at all. They release a new service only when they are sure that it meets or exceeds the absolute best standards
in the market - and they don&rsquo;t care whether a competitor launches a competing service before them. They don&rsquo;t care even
if they don&rsquo;t have a ton of features to start with - they just care about that it should &ldquo;just work&rdquo; and the
documentation is 100 percent updated/correct. For them customer obsession is the single most important thing. There
is another cloud provider whose almost every single service starts life as a public beta(of course with the
disclaimer/warning in all fairness). And personally speaking, sales folks from this provider have actively urged me
to try out their beta, and sometimes going to the extent of saying that, the feature I am looking for is only available
in the beta and that is the recommended technology to use/and the future as of now. This has left me with heartache
and pain and substantially higher number of hours in office.</p>
<h2 id="what-does-it-cost-me---pricing-model-please">What does it cost me - Pricing model please?</h2>
<p>In the money making business, ethics sometimes might get overlooked or de-prioritized albeit temporarily,
much driven by cut-throat competition - I think that&rsquo;s just unfair. For some however, ethics and integrity are
sacrosanct. One provider&rsquo;s pricing model was designed in such a way, that whether I like it or not, a particular
&ldquo;size&rdquo; of the service only allows &ldquo;up to a certain max throughput&rdquo;. Beyond that, I need to switch to the next level
manually myself. BTW, the sales guy did tell me I can do some form of automation to do that switch, for which the
documentation was so archaic, obscure and outdated that it felt really helpless. There is another provider however,
who sold one of their services with a pricing model that is simply based on total messages getting into the system.
It&rsquo;s charged based on per millions of messages. Everything else and the heavy lifting and auto-scaling is internal to
the service. If I needed to a particular max level of throughput in PROD, I just had to raise a simple request and they
updated the limits, at the very same pricing model. Remember the service was priced on millions of messages and not the
&ldquo;hardware&rdquo; tier I was using - BTW there was no such thing even as a hardware tier for this service with these guys.
It was just plain and simple and I was able to move ahead confidently without the fear of avoidable cost overruns due
to mis-configuration to a large extent.</p>
<h2 id="business-model-and-business-ethics">Business model and business ethics</h2>
<p>One provider might sometimes take an approach of repackaging and rebranding a failed service. To the humble coder,
it might appear, the provider deals with the poor uptake and the negative feedback by rebranding the service -
probably without making any substantial change or even without fully addressing the existing issues - with a new
UI perhaps. Another provider has rarely had the need to kill a service because it was designed with at least a ten
year roadmap with lot of thought and foresight put into it. It started years ago, its adoption has only gone north
and the feature set just becomes better with every release.</p>
<h2 id="i-am-a-human-i-commit-mistakes">I am a human, I commit mistakes</h2>
<p>I am a human, I commit mistakes. Treat me like a human, I will thank you for that. I am also a customer,
if you want my loyalty, you got to work towards it and not just get into a volume licensing agreement at an
organizational level. There was one provider whose business/sales strategy appeared to be signing a deal at the
topmost levels of the organization and not being worried too much at a project or program level - kind of one size
fits all. Again there was another provider who actually waived off 16,000 USD when a developer&rsquo;s keys were stolen and
a hacker spun up the most expensive VMs in all the regions in which the services were offered. This provider just
asked me, to convince them that I have now put everything in place to ensure to mitigate such breaches in the future
and have ensured the team is well-trained to avoid mishaps. Narrow escape, but they treated me as a human being.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Folks, I think on one hand this world has day traders out there to make a quick buck(well again, that&rsquo;s what a day
trader&rsquo;s job is, isn&rsquo;t it?). On the other hand there are the guys who are in here for the long run who&rsquo;s business
model is customer obsession. Both of these two extremes and everyone in between is doing perfectly legal business
and they are entitled to do business the way they want while following regulation in the countries where they sell
their services. None of them is forcing you to sign the purchase order. It is up to us to ask the right questions,
the questions that really matter to us, choose the right partners with high business standards, and make the right
decisions - as if our life depends on it. Let&rsquo;s pledge we will do everything in our capacity to make our own lives
easier and save money/time along the way, even if we have to debate with the largest corporations in the world.</p>
<p>Code and build with joy, do the right thing, choose smart, partner with the best, may the best guy win, do your part
to weed out mediocrity, save money and save time for yourself and the planet.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>The Family From Canada</title>
            <link>https://arunkpatra.io/posts/2009/07/the-family-from-canada/</link>
            <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://arunkpatra.io/posts/2009/07/the-family-from-canada/</guid>
            <description>AS MY stay here at California nears its end, I find myself some time at my disposal to just sit back and look back for a while. I met a very wide array of people here, mostly at the Vikings bar where all these oldie bikers show up. Its an old school American bar, and people are friendly. Some master pool players show up sometimes, and my friend Benjamin helped me pick up the basics of the game.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>AS MY stay here at California nears its end, I find myself some time at my disposal to just sit back and look back for a while. I met a very wide array of people here, mostly at the Vikings bar where all these oldie bikers show up. Its an old school American bar, and people are friendly. Some master pool players show up sometimes, and my friend Benjamin helped me pick up the basics of the game. So, everyone over here has a story to tell, eager to share something and then they buy me a drink. Good fellas&hellip;</p>
<p>I have a little story as well to tell. A couple of months after I landed over here, I happened to meet a Canadian family. Well, a Canadian Geese family. There were two of them and they are huge birds. They migrated from Canada to California and made the sprawling grounds and the artificial lake near my work area as their new summer home. Long timers over here at work tell me that Canadian Geese haven&rsquo;t shown up at our office grounds since the last very many years and it was a matter of great excitement for everyone to have them around here once again.</p>
<p>So here they were, happily roaming around the grounds and its a treat to watch them from a distance. I usually grab a coffee every morning and walk over to the grounds to watch them for a while. One fine morning, they were nowhere to be seen. I went over almost to the edge of the grounds to the foothills to see if they are around. Still I couldn&rsquo;t find them. Probably they just didn&rsquo;t like the place. Probably they just took off to some other place&hellip;</p>
<p>Weeks passed by, and I forgot them for a while. Then all of a sudden one morning they were back! And along with them were seven small fat goslings! Oh what a feeling it was to see them back again! And everyone around was so happy about it. For days altogether all our meetings used to start with a brief discussion on the Canadian Geese family. I even did some research and found out the reason as why they were not to be seen for those few weeks. When they incubate the eggs, the parents rarely go out and far from the nest. People told me it was rare to see such large Canadian Geese from the wild to see in California. We were so lucky to have them around. Those geese are very protective about their kids and at least one parent is on the lookout for any possible danger all the time.</p>
<p>I had taken my coffee that day, just like any other day at work and walked over to the grounds to see the geese family. What I saw instead shook me. Instead of the entire family, there was just a single parent and a single gosling to be seen. There were no signs of the rest. I frantically tried to look for them all over the place. But after a short while I had to accept the truth. They were probably eaten up by the coyotes or the raccoons who come down from the other side of the hill at night to hunt. With a heavy heart, i went back to work and spent a disturbed day. Complex thoughts about birth, life, death and our existence kept floating around my head all day and that night. Neither did I talk to anyone that day nor did I do much&hellip;</p>
<p>Although I didn&rsquo;t feel like taking my coffee to the grounds the next day, I kind of involuntarily walked out of door towards the ground. That morning, I didn&rsquo;t find the remaining goose and the gosling. The kind hearted security guard told me that there were feathers all over the place that morning at the back. And she told me another thing which i had expected the least. &lsquo;Don&rsquo;t love anyone so much - it hurts when you loose them&rsquo; she said, smiled and went away. My head started to spin and it lasted a while. And I never went back to the same grounds after that.</p>
<p>Today morning however, I went over there again and took some pictures of the place where I had spent so many happy mornings. So I guess then, I will never forget the kind lady at the security gate i met that day. I did think over what she had said for a few days. And I believe she was probably right. Complex and intense feelings like love, expectation or affection are things that are not made for everyone. They are not for the faint hearted. They are designs for the human mind specifically created by God only for those who can handle it. Its like an extremely potent drug, and unless you can handle it and digest it, you will die of overdose. It does good only to those who balance it out with other things in life. It works out only when its taken in moderation and only when the inner self monitors the use&hellip;</p>
<p>I have always maintained that, at the bottom of all human miseries are two things - expectation and insecurity. Much can I say on those but some other day. All that suffices to say at this juncture is that expectation makes you weak, and weakness makes you insecure. Insecurity is a disease which is extremely difficult to cure. If left untreated it would take fatal forms like suspicion, jealousy, anger, vengeance and the like. Death follows soon thereafter. Not from outside but from inside. What is left then is a walking corpse. You see many of them crossing the street, every day&hellip; little do we realize that tomorrow we could be one of them&hellip;</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>On the Abstract Nature of the Human Mind</title>
            <link>https://arunkpatra.io/posts/2009/07/on-the-abstract-nature-of-the-human-mind/</link>
            <pubDate>Thu, 09 Jul 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://arunkpatra.io/posts/2009/07/on-the-abstract-nature-of-the-human-mind/</guid>
            <description>I THINK I am a born programmer and will be one for the rest of my life. There are very few other things which give me the same amount of satisfaction. But with gradual passage of time something strange has happened.
With time, the kind of designs that I have started creating - and I don&amp;rsquo;t know how or when it happened - no longer appear to follow any standard design pattern.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I THINK I am a born programmer and will be one for the rest of my life. There are very few other things which give me the same amount of satisfaction. But with gradual passage of time something strange has happened.</p>
<p>With time, the kind of designs that I have started creating - and I don&rsquo;t know how or when it happened - no longer appear to follow any standard design pattern. Maybe it is reflective of my own inner self in some way. My designs and models have started taking some strange forms. On a very first look it would appear to the beholder, that below a certain level in the graph, the objects are some in-explicable piece of code which does not say anything. What possible relation could it have with the final objective? They appear to perform some outlandish activity which seemingly is totally unnecessary. What can be achieved in a direct fashion, need not be so abstract after all! We will analyze this, but a bit later&hellip;</p>
<p>Another thing that I see, that the designs have become secretive. Its all hidden under layers and layers of objects about which someone would never get a glimpse of. Why have I started giving the user a singe and absolutely single view of the functionality? Why has it become so generic? At first sight this looks horribly wrong somewhere. But this is not my intent. To counter this problem, I have started giving the user every possible means of talking to me and explaining me what exactly he or she wants! What do I mean? Well, I teach the user a language, and the user just needs to talk to me in that language and tell me what they want. It could be as little or as much of information. If i do not understand what they are saying I don&rsquo;t take any action. But if they do talk the same language and say something that I(read it as the design, the model, and the code) understand, their every request is honored and processed. This gives me power to cater to a very wide kind of users, with their own kind of needs which might be very specific. But they all go through the same gates and must talk the language that I understand. That&rsquo;s just the single limitation.</p>
<p>I have also started resorting to going to extreme lengths to keep things virtually unknown to others. The designs have started evolving in such a way that even objects close to each other would not know what is their relation. Somehow I have started putting in place a master controller who sees everything, watches everything and finds out on its own which switch to press and in what order. Maybe I am coming closer and closer to granting all possible power to the controller. I am trying to give it a mind of its own while the lesser mortals are just pawns which dance to the tunes of the controller? Why? Does it need to be like that?</p>
<p>Yet another something. The designs now seem to try to discover unsaid things all the time. They first make an assumption, and then try to find out if that is valid. Did the user ever indicate something like that? It is not necessary that the user was exact or not, as long as something was said in the language the design understands. If yes, the design now tries to verify the validity first. Does it violate any other aspect of the process? If not, I go ahead and fulfill that request&hellip;</p>
<p>Coming back to the original question on the abstraction and need for it&hellip; To be honest, I hate it and I love it&hellip; Nothing more am I capable of saying - inexplicable.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
