<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>informationtechnology on Marichikā</title>
    <link>https://arunkpatra.io/tags/informationtechnology/</link>
    <description>Recent content in informationtechnology on Marichikā</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://arunkpatra.io/tags/informationtechnology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Argumentative Indian and the Globetrotter</title>
      <link>https://arunkpatra.io/posts/2020/07/the-argumentative-indian-and-the-globetrotter/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://arunkpatra.io/posts/2020/07/the-argumentative-indian-and-the-globetrotter/</guid>
      <description>Flashback 2005 On a rainy August evening, an arduous four legged late night flight from Chennai, India, to San Antonio, TX USA put me on a completely new journey of my professional life. A journey that gave me opportunities to meet people from almost every culture and country. I saw, observed, heard, listened, experienced and lived an incredibly rich and diverse set of cultures. And those experiences included professionalism, work ethics, food, emotional quotient and the purpose of life from a plethora of perspectives.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Architect</title>
      <link>https://arunkpatra.io/posts/2020/07/the-architect/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://arunkpatra.io/posts/2020/07/the-architect/</guid>
      <description>Image © Warner Bros. Pictures, Village Roadshow Pictures
  Who are you? So asked Neo Contrary to what many might think, the Information Technology shop floor is not vastly different from a production line of the manufacturing industry. There are stark similarities. Same things in IT as well; sales, marketing, planning, design, processes, technology, products and people who create those products - in this case, software.
It is but natural to think, that in the IT industry as well, there are many different roles that people play in the shop floor.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
