<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>india on Marichikā</title>
    <link>https://arunkpatra.io/tags/india/</link>
    <description>Recent content in india on Marichikā</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 06 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://arunkpatra.io/tags/india/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Dharmarāja</title>
      <link>https://arunkpatra.io/posts/2020/07/dharmaraja/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://arunkpatra.io/posts/2020/07/dharmaraja/</guid>
      <description>Prologue The Indian way of life is woven with yarns of a multitude of faiths, beliefs and convictions. If the warp of our culture’s fabric is rationale, the weft has to be belief. That fabric is dyed with hues of tradition and rituals, and block printed with rich patterns from Hindu mythology. An extraordinarily rich and complex cultural canvas is the result.
Hindu mythology just like Egyptian, Greek or Norse mythology, plays a very important role in carrying forward human culture.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Argumentative Indian and the Globetrotter</title>
      <link>https://arunkpatra.io/posts/2020/07/the-argumentative-indian-and-the-globetrotter/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://arunkpatra.io/posts/2020/07/the-argumentative-indian-and-the-globetrotter/</guid>
      <description>Flashback 2005 On a rainy August evening, an arduous four legged late night flight from Chennai, India, to San Antonio, TX USA put me on a completely new journey of my professional life. A journey that gave me opportunities to meet people from almost every culture and country. I saw, observed, heard, listened, experienced and lived an incredibly rich and diverse set of cultures. And those experiences included professionalism, work ethics, food, emotional quotient and the purpose of life from a plethora of perspectives.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Online Certifications</title>
      <link>https://arunkpatra.io/posts/2020/06/online-certifications/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://arunkpatra.io/posts/2020/06/online-certifications/</guid>
      <description>The E-Learning and Online Technical Certification Market According to Global Market Insights, the e-Learning market size crossed the USD 200 billion mark in 2019 and is expected to grow at over 8% between 2020 and 2026. This data appears to be pre-Covid19 projections. It&amp;rsquo;s not at all difficult to see that the growth rate of this market is definitely going to go north in the current situations. Its just safe to say for now, that e-learning and online technical certification market is booming and will continue to expand rapidly if not explode altogether.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
